Guide to the ACT UP New York records, 1969, 1982-1997 [bulk 1987-1995]
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
ACT UP New York records
1969, 1982-1997
1987-1995
MssCol 10
10
ACT UP New York (Organization)
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
97.4 linear feet 234 boxes, 4 oversize folders, 4 tubes, 1 oversize item
The AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) was founded in March 1987 at the Lesbian and Gay Community Center in New York City's Greenwich Village as an organization devoted to direct action (demonstrations and civil disobedience) to call the attention of government officials, scientists, drug companies and other corporations, and the general public to the severity of the AIDS crisis and its impact on the lives of individuals. Records of the organization consist of administrative files, minutes, correspondence, records of demonstrations, financial documents, chapter and committee records, subject files, conference notes and programs, published and near-print materials, ephemera, fliers and handbills, photographs, artifacts, posters and placards documenting the organization's efforts.
The AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) was founded in March 1987 at the Lesbian and Gay Community Center in New York City's Greenwich Village as an organization devoted to direct action (demonstrations and civil disobedience) to call the attention of government officials, scientists, drug companies, other corporations, and the general public to the severity of the AIDS crisis and its impact on the lives of individuals. ACT UP New York gained thousands of members in its first four years and expanded to more than 70 chapters worldwide.
On March 24, 1987, only weeks after its founding, ACT UP demonstrated on Wall Street to protest the profiteering of pharmaceutical companies, especially Burroughs Wellcome, manufacturer of AZT. Seventeen people were arrested. Following the demonstrations, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) announced that it would shorten the drug approval process by two years. For ACT UP, demonstrations were the physical result of the theoretical concept of direct action. At its peak, ACT UP, which first created the acronym, then chose the words to fit it, consciously acted in a manner befitting its moniker. As an organization, it spoke and acted out to test the limits of authority. Notably, the organization gained renown for its demonstrations, which captured media attention and brought focus to its messages. During the height of its activity in the early 1990s, ACT UP's demonstrations were theatrical in nature, involving rehearsal and props in addition to research, planning, and publicity. While practicing nonviolent civil disobedience, members often aimed at getting arrested. Arrests drew media attention to both the actions of the protestors and the grievances that sparked their action. This attention might then either embarrass or otherwise motivate the protested party to elicit change.
Through the years ACT UP orchestrated numerous demonstrations that contributed to changes in public policy regarding AIDS. Other notable demonstrations that occurred in 1987 included protests against Northwest Orient Airlines, New York City's Memorial Sloan-Kettering Hospital, and the newly-formed Presidential Commission on AIDS in Washington, DC.
ACT UP New York's Women's Caucus formed and organized its first action when it targeted the offices of Cosmopolitan magazine in January 1988. Five hundred people protested an article that claimed heterosexual women were not at significant risk of contracting AIDS. Celebrating the first anniversary of an ACT UP demonstration in March, the coalition returned to Wall Street where one hundred activists were arrested. The major media coverage this action received helped broadcast central AIDS issues. In October, ACT UP and other AIDS organizations shut down the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) outside of Washington, DC.
In 1989, ACT UP demonstrated at City Hall, the Fifth International Conference on AIDS in Montréal, the New York Stock Exchange, and St. Patrick's Cathedral. ACT UP's Youth Brigade began distributing condoms and safe sex/clean needle information outside New York City schools in October. Following these demonstrations Mayor Ed Koch announced a new housing policy for people with AIDS; Anthony Fauci, director of the AIDS program at the National Institutes of Health, publicly announced the concept of "parallel track," which would make experimental AIDS drugs available to patients outside of formal clinical trials; and Burroughs Wellcome lowered the price of AZT by 20%.
In 1991, ACT UP demonstrated at the Manhattan Criminal Court building; the Department of Correctional Services (DOCS) in Albany, New York; the National Insurance Association in Washington, DC; the New York State office building; President Bush's vacation home in Kennebunkport, Maine; and the White House. The last two demonstrations were part of the "Target Bush" action, which occurred throughout the month of September. It was on January 22, 1991, however, when one of the highest profile actions in the group's history occurred. Activists invaded the MacNeil/Lehrer NewsHour while America was tuned in for news of the Persian Gulf War. The protesters stormed in shouting, "Fight AIDS - Not Arabs!" and chained themselves to the anchors' desks. This dramatic interruption increased the media's interest in the following day's series of protests that ACT UP declared a "Day of Desperation," implying that with AIDS, every day is a day of desperation.
While the media, and thus the public, focused on the demonstrations that ACT UP orchestrated, the coalition spent most of its time doing other types of work. A General Meeting was held every Monday night that included announcements, life-saving information, actions in development, follow-ups on previous actions, zap proposals, and operational requests. To clarify, ACT UP defined actions as public protests that were characterized by a planning period, promotion, and large turnout; zaps addressed immediate concerns and usually had more specific targets. At least during its first decade, a literature table was set up at each meeting that included information for general distribution while a fundraising table sold T-shirts, stickers, books, posters, buttons, postcards, and mugs; attendees were asked to donate $3.00 to help pay the rent.
Much of ACT UP's work from 1987-1995 was done in affinity groups, committees, working groups, and caucuses devoted to particular topics. Some groups, particularly working groups, were short-lived, designed to address short-term projects or activities. Generally, committees had longer lives. Some of the larger groups were the Alternative and Holistic Treatment committee, Latina/o caucus, Media committee, Needle Exchange committee, Prison Issues committee, Treatment and Data committee, and YELL (Youth Education Life Line).
As ACT UP declared, their members advised and informed in addition to participating in demonstrations. A large and important committee, Treatment and Data, grew to be vital to this mission. In June 1990, Treatment and Data issued its "1990 Treatment Agenda," which outlined the direction it believed the AIDS research community should take. In November, the committee released the "Countdown 18 Months Plan," a set of scientific procedures and demands to implement treatment and research for the top opportunistic infections. ACT UP members attended international conferences on AIDS and stayed up to date on traditional and alternative treatments that might help the AIDS community, creating their own AIDS library.
Out of ACT UP other noteworthy AIDS organizations arose: Gran Fury, an artists collective of AIDS activists, formed out of ACT UP's involvement with "Let the Record Show.. ." at The New Museum of Contemporary Art in 1987, and continued to be associated with the group by creating many of their notable graphics; Queer Nation, a short-lived radical, militant gay and lesbian activist organization dedicated to visibility; and the Treatment Action Group (TAG), an organization dedicated to AIDS treatment and cure research. Also associated with ACT UP New York was the Silence = Death Project, the anonymous group of men that created the Silence = Death poster that became a rallying point for the early AIDS movement.
ACT UP New York was at its peak of activity during the early 1990s. By 1996, the radically democratic organization harbored internal divisions over tactics and its relationship to both the AIDS and gay/lesbian movements. Divided, and with declining membership due to death and burnout, the coalition endured financial troubles, left their longtime workspace on West 29th Street, and donated their records to the New York Public Library. This end of an era for ACT UP coincided with a diminishing sense of crisis. In America, the combination of new treatments and greater availability, coupled with greater public education, made it possible to have AIDS and live. Although the coalition still exists at the time of this writing, its public visibility has waned.
Sources: Greenberg, Jon. "ACT UP Explained." ACT UP New York. http://www.actupny.org/documents/greenbergAU.html (accessed Mar. 20, 2008).
Rimmerman, Craig A. "ACT UP." The Encyclopedia of AIDS. Ed. by Raymond A. Smith. Chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn, 1998. http://thebody.com/content/art14001.html (accessed Feb. 22, 2008).
The ACT UP New York records contain administrative files; minutes; correspondence; action, demonstration, and zap records; financial records; chapter records; committee records; subject files; conference notes and programs; published and near-print material; ephemera, fliers, and handbills; photographs and slides; artifacts; posters and placards.
These records document a very active grassroots organization committed to focusing the world's attention on the AIDS crisis. Arranged in fifteen series, the first three series provide a basic overview of ACT UP that is expanded upon throughout the collection.
Strengths of this collection include its documentation of ACT UP's expertise at identifying, locating, and keeping abreast of medical and experimental treatments. Since this knowledge extended throughout the organization, documentation can be found in multiple series, including: Series VIII. Committees, particularly the Alternative and Holistic, Media, and Treatment and Data committees; and Series IX. Conferences. The organization also monitored society's attitudes toward and treatment of individuals with AIDS/HIV. It accomplished these tasks, in part, by collecting articles from medical literature and the popular press; publications and related material from pharmaceutical companies, federal, state, and local governments which can be found in Series X. Publications and near-print materials. While ACT UP sought to find a solution to the crisis, it remembered those individuals who succumbed to AIDS by maintaining a small obituary file, as well as other AIDS-related subject files, in Series VIII. Subjects.
One of the strengths of this collection is its documentation of the way in which ACT UP offered its members the opportunity to express ideas, innovations, and interests for the cause. As ACT UP member Jon Greenberg noted, the group, and its demonstrations in particular, offered empowerment to its members. This empowerment can be seen in the collection of impressive posters and placards in Series XIV which were created by members for demonstrations and actions. On a smaller creative scale, Series XI. Ephemera, fliers, and handbills contains handouts used to publicize meetings, provide information, and promote actions. The collection also offers insight into how ACT UP interacted with other organizations concerned with similar issues, documentation of which can be found throughout multiple series, including: Series III. Correspondence; Series XI. Ephemera, fliers, and handbills; and Series XIV. Posters and placards.
The majority of this collection has been microfilmed. Once a folder has been located in the container list below, use the microfilm guide to ascertain the order in which items appear on the microfilm reel. Items that were not filmed are noted at the box or folder level; entire series that were not filmed are noted in their series description.
The ACT UP New York Records are organized in the following series:
Series I. Administrative/Organizational history, 1988-1989, n.d.
Series II. Minutes, 1987-1994
Series III. Correspondence, 1987-1995, n.d.
Series IV. Actions, demonstrations, and zaps, 1987-1995, n.d.
Series V. Financial records, 1989-1994 [?], n.d.
Series VI. Chapters, 1986-1993, n.d.
Series VII. Committees, 1985-1995, n.d.
Series VIII. Subjects, 1982-1995, n.d.
Series IX. Conferences, 1983-1994
Series X. Published and near-print materials, 1969, 1982-1995, n.d.
Series XI. Ephemera, fliers, and handbills, 1988-1993, n.d.
Series XII. Photographs and slides, 1987-1989, n.d.
Series XIII. Artifacts, circa 1987-1990, 1992, circa 1994, 1997, n.d.
Series XIV. Posters and placards, 1986, circa 1988-circa 1995, 1997, n.d.
Series XV. Addenda, 1985-1997, n.d.
Received from ACT UP New York, 1995; additions received from Ron Goldberg, Jack Ben Levi, Conyers Thompson, and Stephen Shapiro, 1992-1997.
ACT UP Oral History Project videotapes, 2002-2005. The New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division (Information can also be found on their website: http://www.actuporalhistory.org/interviews/index.html).
AIDS Activist Videotape Collection. The New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division.
AIDS and Adolescents Network of New York records, 1987-1999. The New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Gran Fury collection, 1987-1995. The New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division.
International Gay Information Center collection, 1951-1994. The New York Public Library, Manuscripts and Archives Division.
The majority of the collection is available on microfilm in the Manuscripts and Archives Division. ACT UP New York posters and placards are reproduced in the NYPL Digital Gallery: http://digitalgallery.nypl.org/nypldigital/dgkeysearchresult.cfm?parent_id=1060819&word=.
ACT UP New York (Organization); AIDS (Disease); AIDS (Disease) -- Political aspects; AIDS (Disease) -- Social aspects; AIDS (Disease) and the arts; AIDS (Disease) in mass media; AIDS activists; Gay activists -- New York (State) -- New York; Artifacts; Ephemera; Fliers (printed matter); Photographs; Posters; Slides (Photographs); Stickers
- Series I. Administrative/Organizational history, 1988-1989, n.d.; 556008; 2 boxes
  Series I. Administrative/Organizational history is arranged alphabetically and provides an overview of the operations of ACT UP. It contains the organization's administrative manual, administrative handbook, and basic information handbook (AIDS 101). ACT UP's Capsule History highlights important events in the history of the organization. By-laws and related material complete the series. See Series XV. Addenda for additional administrative materials.
  - Administrator's manual, 1988 Jun-1989 Feb, n.d; 556009 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - By-laws and related materials, 556010 (Reel 1, Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Capsule history, n.d.; 556011; See Series XV. Addenda for additional materials. (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Handbooks, 556012
    - Hernandez, Vic. AIDS 101., circa 1991 Apr, 1992; 556013; Draft and final version (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Information, 1988-1989, n.d.; 556014; Includes: New Members, FDA Action 1988, AIDS Drugs Now 1989, Target City Hall 1989, and Fact Sheets. (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - The Quest for Healthcare: ACT UP's First Struggle, n.d.; 556015 (Reel 1, Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Working documents, 556016
    - Additional material, n.d.; 556017 (Reel 1, Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Working document and memo of law, 556018 (Reel 1, Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II. Minutes, 1987-1994; 556019; 4 boxes
  Series II. Minutes is arranged chronologically and contains a combination of handwritten and typed notes documenting the organization's meetings. The minutes provide information about the earliest days of ACT UP, beginning in the late 1980s through its maturity in the 1990s. The documents focus on organizational procedures and provide information about issues of concern to their members. The minutes provide a chronology of pertinent issues, as well as document the fluctuation in their importance. Some basic issues of finances and fundraising are also covered in this series; see Series V. Financial records for more information. Chapter minutes are filed with their respective chapters; see Series VI. Chapters.
  - 1987 Mar-1988 Dec, 556020 (Reel 2, Box 3, Folder 1-19)
  - 1989 Jan-Oct, 556021 (Reel 2, Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  - 1989 Nov-1990 Sept, 556022 (Reel 3, Box 4, Folder 6-14)
  - 1990 Oct-1992 Apr, 556023 (Reel 3, Box 5, Folder 1-9)
  - 1992 May-Dec, 556024 (Reel 4, Box 5, Folder 10-17)
  - 1993-1994, 556025 (Reel 4, Box 6, Folder 1-3)
- Series III. Correspondence, 1987-1995, n.d.; 556026; 6 boxes
  In Series III. Correspondence, general correspondence is arranged chronologically and the remaining material is arranged alphabetically. This series provides some overview of ACT UP's relationship with state and city governments, corporations, the public, and organizations with similar goals.
  - 1987 [Jan]-1988 Jul, 556027 (Reel 5, Box 7, Folder 1-11)
  - 1988 Aug-1989, 556028 (Reel 5, Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - 1990-1991, 556029 (Reel 6, Box 8, Folder 5-11)
  - 1992-1995, 556030 (Reel 6, Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - n.d, 556031 (Reel 7, Box 9, Folder 7)
  - ACT NOW, n.d.; 556032 (Reel 8, Box 11, Folder 4)
  - ACT UP Reports (Fall/Winter 1990), no.1-2 (1991, 556033 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Administrative support team, n.d.; 556034; Blank forms (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Barbara McClintock Project to Cure AIDS, n.d.; 556035; Later known as the AIDS Cure Project. (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Biographies, 556036 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Contacts, phone numbers, addresses, n.d.; 556037 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 2)
  - General meeting agenda, 556038; Blank forms (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 4)
  - A His and Herstory of Queer Activism, 1989 Jun; 556039 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Lawyer directory, n.d.; 556040 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mailing lists, 556041
    - n.d, 556042 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 6)
    - n.d, 556043 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 8-10)
    - CDC (Center for Disease Control), n.d.; 556044 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Media lists, n.d.; 556045 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Network, 1991 Jun; 1993 Aug 9; 1994 May 24, Jun 6, n.d; 556046; See Series XV. Addenda for additional materials. (Reel 7, Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Network, 1991 Sep-Oct, 1992 Jan-1993 Feb, n.d; 556047; See Series XV. Addenda for additional materials. (Reel 8, Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Parliamentary procedures, n.d.; 556048 (Reel 8, Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Press releases, 556049
    - n.d, 556050 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 8)
    - AIDS Activists Mock "Snake Oil" Machinations, 1993; 556051 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Information, n.d.; 556052 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Reports: Miscellaneous, n.d.; 556053 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Sign up forms, n.d.; 556054 (Reel 7, Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Stop AIDS buzzwords, n.d.; 556055 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Teach-in for the CDC action, 1990 Dec 3; 556056 (Reel 8, Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Telephone lists, n.d.; 556057; Not microfilmed (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Workspace, n.d.; 556058 (Reel 8, Box 11, Folder 6-7)
- Series IV. Actions, demonstrations, and zaps, 1987-1995, n.d.; 556059; 7 boxes
  Series IV. Actions, demonstrations, and zaps, organized chronologically, dramatically illustrates the prolific events that ACT UP organized, participated in, and co-sponsored. ACT UP defined actions as planned public protests or demonstrations that targeted an individual or organization. Organized by a working group and approved in advance by the ACT UP floor, actions were characterized by a planning period, promotion, and a large turnout. On the other hand, zaps addressed immediate issues and usually had more specific targets. The targets were bombarded with correspondence, telephone calls, faxes, picketing, and/or invaded office space. This series documents the activities for which ACT UP is most famous and should be considered in concert with Series XI. Ephemera, fliers, and handbills, Series XIII. Artifacts, and Series XIV. Posters and placards.
  - Demonstration master list, 1987-1991; 556060 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 1)
  - 1987, 556061
    - Tax action, New York, 1987 Apr 15; 556062 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 3)
    - White House action, 1987 Jun 1; 556063 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Federal Plaza action, New York, 1987 Jun 30; 556064 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Money for AIDS action, New York, 1987 Dec 1; 556065 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Demonstrations, 1987; 556066 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 2)
  - 1988, 556067
    - Cosmopolitan magazine demonstration, New York, 1988 Jan 15; 556068 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Presidential Commission [on AIDS] action, New York, 1988 Feb 18; 556069 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Wall Street action, New York, 1988 Mar 24; 556070 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 12)
    - National Spring AIDS action, New York, 1988 Apr 29-May 7; 556071 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Democratic convention, Atlanta, Georgia, 1988 Jul; 556072 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Republican convention action, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1988 Aug; 556073 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Freedom ride south, 1988 Summer; 556074 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 13)
    - FDA action, Rockville, Maryland, 556075
      - 1988 Oct 11, 556076 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 17-18)
      - 1988 Oct 11, 556077 (Reel 9, Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Demonstrations, 1988; 556078 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 9)
  - 1989, 556079
    - City Hall action, New York, 556080
      - 1989 Mar 28, 556081 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 4)
      - 1989 Mar 28, 556082 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 6-8)
      - 1989 Mar 28, 556083 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 10)
    - South Carolina, 556084
      - 1989 Apr 20, 556085 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 3)
      - 1989 Apr 21, 556086 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Burroughs Wellcome, New York and Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, 556087
      - 1989 Apr 25, 556088 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 5)
      - 1989 Apr 25, 556089 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Provincetown gay pride and follow-up, Provincetown, Massachusetts, 1989 Jul-Aug; 556090 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 11)
    - New York Stock Exchange action, New York, 1989 Sep 14-15; 556091 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 12-13)
    - Stop the Church, St. Patrick's Cathedral, New York, 556092
      - 1989 Dec 10, 556093 (Reel 10, Box 15, Folder 1-2)
      - Demonstration and proceedings in court, 1989 Dec 10, n.d; 556094 (Reel 11, Box 15, Folder 3-5)
    - Demonstrations, 1989; 556095 (Reel 10, Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 1990, 556096
    - Centers for Disease Control (CDC) and sodomy action, Atlanta, Georgia, 1990 Jan; 556097 (Reel 11, Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Albany action, Albany, New York, 556098; See Series XV. Addenda for additional materials.
      - 1990 Mar 28, 556099 (Reel 11, Box 16, Folder 2)
      - 1990 Mar 28, 556100 (Reel 9, Box 13, Folder 11)
    - National AIDS action for healthcare, Chicago, Illinois, 556101
      - 1990 Apr 21-23, 556102 (Reel 11, Box 16, Folder 3)
      - 1990 Apr, 556103 (Reel 12, Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Healthcare action, Washington, DC, 1989 Dec, 1990 Mar and May; 556104 (Reel 14, Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Storm the National Institutes of Health (NIH), Bethesda, Maryland, 556105
      - 1990 May 21, 556106 (Reel 11, Box 16, Folder 5)
      - 1990 May 21, 556107 (Reel 12, Box 16, Folder 11)